All right, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is כ"ד. chaf
dalet. We pick up with the משנה Mishnah on the bottom of
כ"ג עמוד ב', chaf gimmel amud bet, and we had just turned
about two women who had been taken captive. And the big חידוש
chidush that although they're not believed on themselves, if we have witnesses
that they were taken captive, they are believed to testify on one
another, even if there's a concern of possible concern which the גמרא
Gemara wasn't explicit about then, it'll be explicit about today, a possible
concern about reciprocity. But not only that, we believe in עד אחד,
ed echad, and we said that even in the גמרא, Gemara, that
even if it's one against one, one עד ed says that she
was raped and one עד ed says she was not, and even
if the one that says she's not is normally the weaker עד
ed in terms of הלכה, halacha, or would be a case of
a woman against a man, which in
עדות edus is
the woman's in a weaker status. Nevertheless, we always believe the one
that says she was not. So again, similar to things we've had
in יבמות, Yevamos, a particular leniency that we do in terms of
believing the עד ed that says that she was not raped even
in עד אחד, ed echad, even somebody who's not normally seen as
a כשר עד. kosher ed. We'll see more about that later. Okay,
now we move on to the next
משנה, Mishnah, which is a similar issue.
וכן שני אנשים זה אומר כהן אני וזה אומר כהן אני. V'chein
shnei anashim, zeh omer kohen ani v'zeh omer kohen ani. Two men,
one says that I'm a כהן kohen and the other says that
I'm a כהן. kohen.
אינם נאמנים, Einam neemanim, they're not believed about themselves if we didn't
already have a חזקה, chazaka, have a tradition and an established assumption
that they were a כהן. kohen. And therefore we don't give them
תרומה. Terumah. Okay, because
they're coming to the threshing floor and they're saying or more they're
coming to the threshing floor and they're saying give me the תרומה.
Terumah. So he says, well how do I know how would I
know you're a כהן? kohen? Well, I say I'm a כהן. kohen.
So we don't believe them. ובזמן שהן מעידין זה את זה, U'bizman
she-heim me'idim zeh et zeh, but similar to what we found up
by the women who were captive, if they testify about one another,
the two of them show up at the threshing floor and they
both say he's a כהן, kohen, he says he's a כהן, kohen,
so give us both תרומה. Terumah. So again, that's a case that
you could be concerned about some type of a collusion. Nevertheless, הרי
אלו נאמנים, harei eilu neemanim, they are believed in order to give
them תרומה. Terumah. So that's the חידוש chidush is number one that
you believe in עד אחד ed echad that somebody is a כהן
kohen for the purposes of תרומה. Terumah. And number two is that
you believe it even in possibilities where there's issues of collusion or
reciprocity going on here. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says, אין מעלין לכהונה על פי עד אחד. ein ma'alin
l'kehunah al pi ed echad. No, כהונה kehunah you don't trust based
on one witness. Okay, so it's not good enough. אמר רבי אליעזר,
Amar Rabbi Eliezer, אימתי, eimasai, when is this true? במקום שיש עוררין,
Bimkom she-yesh orerim, when would I concede רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda point
that one witness would not be good? If there was an actual
concrete challenge raised against this person's כהונה kehunah status. אבל במקום שאין
עוררין, Aval bimkom she-ein orerim, if there's no concrete challenge, we just
don't know what this person's identity is.
מעלין לכהונה על פי עד אחד, Ma'alin l'kehunah al pi ed echad,
you could assume raise somebody to כהונה, kehunah, assume somebody is a
כהן kohen on the basis of one witness. Okay, so now we
have three opinions. One is well one that's not clear that says
you believe in עד אחד. ed echad. The position of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that says, did I skip the line by the way?
No, I didn't. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says that you do
not
and you do not trust an עד אחד ed echad for this.
And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that reiterates what the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says and says that you do, however he concedes that if
there's a concrete challenge raised against the person, you do not. The
גמרא Gemara will assume that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer might not concede
the case of, not only does he not concede the case when
there's עוררין, orerin, he might not concede the case when there are
two of them showing up and there's a concern of collusion. He
might only accept an עד אחד ed echad in the standard case,
but not in the special case of the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
let's finish the
משנה, Mishnah, where two of them show up and they're testifying on
one another. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer,
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says, משום רבי שמעון
בן הסגן, mishum Rabbi Shimon ben HaSgan, ממנו, mimeno, he says בן
הסגן. ben HaSgan.
Right, that's true. Okay. מעלין לכהונה על פי עד אחד. Ma'alin l'kehunah
al pi ed echad. You can trust an עד אחד. ed echad.
That is not clear at all how he is different than any
of the two opinions that preceded him. So again, you have תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma that says you can do it even in the
case where there might be collusion. You have רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that says you cannot do it if a concrete challenge has been
raised and the גמרא Gemara will say
he might not agree either in the case of possible collusion. It
might only be when one person they're not testifying about one another.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you do not trust an עד אחד
ed echad for this and רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel says also that you do, like the first two opinions you
do,
but not clear how he differs from either of the first two
opinions. Yes, Michael?
I may have discussed this before I came in but when we
say about נאמנות, ne'emanus, is this more for or only for ממונות
mammonus kind of things?
if he wants to get up and דוכן? duchen? I mean.
All right, so excellent. So that's going to be most of today's
דף. daf. Yes.
Why don't you read the משנה Mishnah of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
clarifying רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
It could be. The גמרא gemara *Gemara* actually discusses when somebody says
אימתי *eimatai*, if it's לחלוק *lachlok* or if it's come to clarify
or to disagree. Could be. But Rabbi Yehuda sounds more categorical, so
Rabbi Eliezer might be trying to contextualize and limit Rabbi Yehuda, but
it sounds like that Rabbi Yehuda was a broader statement. The גמרא
gemara *Gemara* sees it as debate. It could be he's claiming that's
what Rabbi Yehuda meant, but it's not so פשוט *pashut* that that
is what Rabbi Yehuda meant. Okay, let's look at the גמרא gemara
*Gemara*. כל הני למה לי *Kol hanei lama li*: Why do I
need all of these? All of these means all of the משניות
*mishnayot* that we just had over the last few days
about הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar הוא הפה שהתיר *ha’peh she’asar hu ha’peh
she’hitir*, okay? So why do I need all of them? Of course,
these last two are not הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar. הוא הפה שהתיר
*ha’peh she’asar hu ha’peh she’hitir*. They're just about נאמנות *ne’emanut* without a
הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar *peh she’asar*, you know? The last two are
particularly a חידוש chiddush, *chiddush* about being trusted, עד אחד eid echad
*ed echad* about שבויה shvuya, *shvuya* and trusting an עד אחד eid
echad *ed echad* about כהן kohen *Kohen*. But anyway, what's but there
seems to be a lot of repetition. Why I need all of
these? So דאי תנא מודה רבי יהושע *De’i tana modeh Rabbi Yehoshua*,
if it had the first case of the פרק perek *perek* where
Rabbi Yehoshua agrees in the case of the guy says that this
field was your father's and I bought it from you, that and
therefore that's a הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar, *peh she’asar* and we believe
the guy משום דאיכא דררא דממונא *mishum de’ika drara demamona*, because there
is a דררא דממונא *drara demamona*. What does the word דררא *drara*
mean? רש״י *Rashi* often says דררא *drara* means a loss of money.
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says it means you have a connection to money.
So the way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* explains this is easier, that if
the guy's already on the field, he's been working on the field
and he says, this field that I'm on, it used to be
your father's and I bought it, so it's not such a big
חידוש chiddush *chiddush* that we say הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar *peh she’asar*.
You're already in possession of the field, right?
So to so that's more easy that we would say הפה שאסר
ha'peh she'asar *peh she’asar* as opposed to other cases where there might
not be the case. Okay, רש״י *Rashi* says דררא דממונא *drara demamona*
here means that if he were lying he would lose the field,
so therefore it's much clearer that when he says the field was
your father's, that the second part of the statement, but I bought
it from him, is part of the same statement. Because רש״י *Rashi*
and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos*, you know, in many of these scenarios, the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* is never says it explicitly, but say that the
הפה שאסר ha'peh she'asar, *peh she’asar* has to be like the same
statement. Maybe even the two parts have to be תוך כדי דיבור
*toch k’dei dibbur* of one another. So for רש״י *Rashi*, part of
the חידוש chiddush *chiddush*, right, because otherwise it's like no, we believe
when you said it was his field ten days ago, now we're
not going to believe you when you said you bought it from,
you know, you bought it from the father. So it has to
be if it has to be the same statement, רש״י *Rashi* says
that maybe that's the point, that if I know the first half
of the statement is going to make me lose money, then there's
no question that the end of the sentence was meant to qualify
and to be part of the first part of the statement. But
you might not always say that. Sometimes you might be more inclined
to see them as two different statements. But here, where money's at
stake, clearly it's all one statement.
That's the way דררא *drara* means well, that's the debate.
Well, that is the debate. Nobody knows. It probably means more of
a connection to money, but רש״י *Rashi* says it means a loss
of money.
And the ראש *Rosh* says there is an asmakhta that רש״י *Rashi*
says דמוחזק בשדה *demuchzak basadeh*. It sounds like it's like from דיור
*diyur*, like he's literally living
no, because דררא דממונא *drara demamona* is not used just by just
by real estate. דררא דממונא *drara demamona* is a common phrase that's
used. All right, anyway, it means there's a debate whether it means
שייכות ממון *shaychus mamon* or הפסד ממון *hefsed mamon*. Okay, anyway, but
so that's what רש״י *Rashi* says. So again, what רש״י *Rashi*’s important
to make us realize that part of a thing that the גמרא
Gemara. *Gemara* never was explicit about about about about הפה שאסר ha'peh
she'asar, *peh she’asar* is what are the parameters of seeing it as
the same statement, and therefore רש״י *Rashi* emphasizes that because there's money
at stake, he's clearly meant to end his statement and it's the
same statement. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* again says the simpler point that he's
on the field, so obviously we're more prepared to believe him. So
that was the case, the easier case about being on the field
and saying, I it was your father's and I bought it from
him. Okay, אבל עדים edim דליכא דררא דממונא *Aval edim de’leika drara
demamona*, in the case of witnesses that are saying, you know, this
is our signature, but we were קטנים *ktanim*, we were אנוסים *anusim*,
we were קרובים *krovim*, so you don't have any of these things.
It's not like the money is in the possession of the person
they want, right? They're maybe testifying to a document of a of
a loan. So the the money actually has to change hands, number
one. And number two, or well actually forget that, because anyway point
is they are not in possession of the money that they own.
Number two, they're not the ones who are at stake of losing
money. So אימא לא lo. *eima lo*, maybe you wouldn't say הפה
שאסר *peh she’asar* in that case. Okay, so that's why you needed
the case of the עדים *edim*. ואי תנא עדים *Ve’i tana edim*,
if it had just said the הפה שאסר *peh she’asar* case in
the case of עדים *edim*,
משום דלעלמא *mishum de’le’alma*, I'm more prepared to believe the second part
of their statement because they're helping somebody else, okay? They're helping the
לוה *loveh*. אבל איהו *Aval ihu*, but if he says, this was
your father's field and I purchased it for myself, לנפשיה *le’nafshei*, that
the second part of the statement is coming to help himself, אימא
לא *eima lo*, maybe I wouldn't believe him. So that's why I
needed both the case of the field and the case of the
witnesses. As תוספות tosafot *Tosafos* points out, if you remember, the case
of the witnesses had a lot of חידושים *chiddushim* as well, that
you might say that once they triggered the validity of the שטר
shtar *shtar* in the first half of their statement, they're not believed
to make the second part of their statement because now they're going
up against the שטר *shtar*. So you needed two those two things,
the case of witnesses with the שטר *shtar* and the case of
a guy keeping believed that the field that he purchased the field.
ואשמעינן הני תרתי *Ve’ashmeinan hanei tarti*, and it had us say those
two, משום דממונא *mishum de’mamona*. Okay, we said הפה שאסר *peh she’asar*
by monetary issues. אבל אשת איש *Aval eishes ish*, a woman who
says that she was married and then divorced, where there's a whole
question about her real, you know, status of איסור issur, והיתר *issur
ve’hetter*, דאיסורא *de’issura*, and it's a very weighty issue, אימא לא *eima
lo*, maybe we wouldn't believe the second part of the statement. Okay,
נשביתי וטהורה אני למה לי? So that's when the woman says I
was married and got divorced. Why do I need the second part
of the משנה mishna that we did yesterday or two days ago
where she says I was captive and I was not raped, right?
If the woman is believed that she was divorced, which is a
more weighty איסור, issur, certainly she should be believed that she was
not raped. Okay, משום דקבעי למתני ואם נישאת לאחד מעדיה הרי זו
לא תצא. mishum d'kaba'i le'misni v'im nises le'achad me'adeha harei zo lo
seitzei. Ah, you're right. We don't need to tell you הפה שאסר
there, but what we do need to tell you is is that
she can stay married to the second guy if the witnesses that
she was captive came after she married or the כהן kohen. after
she had married the כהן. kohen Okay, and therefore we need to
tell you the case about captive, about captive, in
the case of potential rape.
Potential rape. She married the כהן kohen? and then witnesses came that
said that she had been captive. No, not that she had been
raped, then we would make her get divorced. Okay, then there'd be
concrete evidence of that. The witnesses said that she had been taken
captive, so you no longer can apply הפה שאסר. Then she's no
longer believed to say she had been raped. Right. Exactly. So she
got married and then witnesses came and said she was captive, you
lose the הפה שאסר and nevertheless we don't make you get divorced.
הניחא למאן דמתני לסיפא, ha'nicha le'man de'masni le'saifa, that's good according to
the one that says that we only don't force a divorce in
the case about captivity, so we had to discuss the captivity case.
אלא למאן דמתני לרישא, ela le'man de'masni le'reisha, but remember there's one
who said that even in the case where witnesses said she had
been married and now there's no evidence that she had been divorced,
there's no הפה שאסר, there's no evidence and nevertheless we don't make
her leave her second husband, which is a huge חידוש, chiddush right?
And we only said it's because חזקה אין אשה מזלזלת בנפשה chazakah
ein isha mezalzelis benafshah and so on. Okay, but there is an
opinion that says that even when she says I was married and
divorced and got married on the basis of it to a second
guy, and then witnesses say she had been married, so now there's
testimony she'd been married and no evidence of divorce, we let her
stay married. So if that's true, so why do we need the
case about being captive at all? We've already said the big חידוש
chiddush. that you say הפה שאסר about her being divorced, which is
a much bigger
weighty weighty status than the question of being
raped, and you say that we even let her stay married to
the second guy even if witnesses said that she had been already
married if that came after she had married the second guy. So
the divorce case is obvious, the case of captivity is obvious, why
do we need it?
This is just דעת יחיד da'as yachid though, no?
I mean there's two ways of reading the משנה. mishna. So if
you read the משנה mishna that way, the משנה mishna says אם
באו עדים im ba'u eidim she can stay married.
Exactly, why do you need at all the case of captivity? Okay,
the case of marriage is the bigger חידוש chiddush? that you say
הפה שאסר and the bigger חידוש chiddush that you let her stay
married. So the גמרא Gemara says no, משום דקבעי למתני שתי נשים
שנשבו, mishum d'kaba'i le'misni shtei nashim she'nishbu, because we wanted to get
to the משנה mishna we read yesterday that talked about believing women
who were both taken captive about one another. Okay, and therefore we
wanted to introduce the case of captivity. You're right, in terms of
הפה שאסר, captivity was not a חידוש. chiddush But we wanted to
introduce the case of captivity to get to the case of, forget
הפה שאסר, one woman is believed, two women who are captive are
believed on one another, which tells you the idea number one that
you believe an עד אחד eid echad relating to these captivity issues.
And number two, you even and a woman, and number three, that
you even believe it if there's a concern of גומלין, gomlin, of
collusion, which is now the גמרא's Gemara next point. Okay, so
okay, ושתי נשים שנשבו למה לי? v'shtei nashim she'nishbu lamah li? What's
the חידוש? chiddush So it doesn't just say the חידוש chiddush is
you believe an עד אחד eid echad. and a woman, actually we're
going to have a משנה mishna later that says that about believing
an עד אחד eid echad by cases of captivity. So what's the
unique חידוש chiddush, of the case of the two women? מהו דתימא
ניחוש לגומלין, mahu de'seima nichosh le'gomlin, because I might say let's be
concerned about גומלין. gomlin. גומלין gomlin here means reciprocity. I'll say that
you weren't raped if you say that I wasn't raped. Okay, so
when they're both saying it about one another, it's a bigger חידוש
chiddush? than just believing an עד אחד. ed echad So קא משמע
לן ka mashma lan that we're not concerned about that. That's why
you needed the case about the two women testifying on one another.
וכן שני אנשים למה לי? v'chein shenei anashim lamah li? Why do
I need the משנה mishna we just read about the two men
about the כהן? kohen. Again, I could say the חידוש chiddush is
that you believe an עד אחד ed echad that somebody is a
כהן. kohen. That's also a חידוש, chiddush at least... so the גמרא
gemara says no, משום דקבעי למתני פלוגתא דרבי יהודה ורבנן, mishum d'kaba'i
le'misni plugta de'Rabbi Yehuda ve'Rabanan, because we see there's a debate about
a כהן. kohen. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that even if you
believe let's say about the issue of captivity, you don't necessarily believe
about somebody being a כהן. kohen Why would it be different? So
there you could, so number one, the easiest answer is is that
the issue of captivity is a שבויה, shvuya. it's a ספק, safek,
so our principle is שבויה הקלו, shvuya hekulu, Rabbis were lenient around
this issue about a woman taken captive and they were more prepared
to believe that she was okay. Okay, so that's one reason why
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda might be more strict by the case of
כהן kohen than שבויה. The other reason as we're going to see
in a few minutes is that once you start allowing your כהן
kohen. to eat תרומה, terumah, okay, that's an איסור, issur but you
know what, I mean a woman who was raped is also in
an איסור to marry a כהן. kohen So you could say תרומה
terumah is a חיוב מיתה, chiyuv misah, maybe it's more weighty that
reason. But the other reason the גמרא's Gemara going to explicitly address
is that if you start letting your כהן kohen eat תרומה, terumah,
then people will think he's a כהן kohen and then they'll allow
him to do other things and in terms of marriage issues they'll
believe he's a כהן kohen and so on and so forth. So
כהן Kohen, is more consequential in other areas.
דווקא *davka* marrying מיוחסות *meyuchasot* and whatever. That's true. Well, it's also
about, but it's also about דוכנן *duchaning*. We'll see all that. But
anyway, by a כהן Kohen. *kohen*, there's going to be a sort
of ripple effect of doing this, and therefore we might be more
concerned, okay? So yes, we believe עד eid. אחד *eid echad* both
by שבויה *shvuya* and by כהן Kohen *kohen*. We're not concerned about
גומלין *gomlin*. But nevertheless, by כהן Kohen *kohen*, there are special issues,
again, maybe because we're particularly lenient by שבויה *shvuya*, maybe because by
כהן kohen *kohen*, there's also this issue about how do we take
the fact that he's eating תרומה trumah. *truma* and then it might
get translated into other things as well. Yes, Michael?
Why don't we bring in the other stuff from פרקים *perakim* before,
like she says מוכת עץ *mukat etz* and all that kind of
thing?
Well, this isn't a פה שאסר *peh she'asar* case, right? I mean,
so we're within the פה שאסר *peh she'asar* categories and we're saying
the believing of the עד eid אחד *eid echad* about somebody else.
I mean, yeah, those were interesting too, but those were just not
the same theme that we're talking about. Yeah?
There was once, do you remember that you laid out once a
paradigm?
That was מיגו *migo*, not פה שאסר *peh she'asar*.
Yeah. Do you remember there was this once of time you laid
out a paradigm of different types of איסורים *issurim*, in other words,
one איסור *issur* that was more חמור *chamur* than another, but another
that had more ramifications in different areas and there was like a...
Were you talking about like איסור כולל *issur kollel* and איסור מוסיף
*issur mosif*? Exactly. So that's about איסור חל על איסור *issur chal
al issur*. Yeah, so that's not exactly comparable. But yes. But I
mean, you know, but it is always important to think about like
what are the different, which one is more weighty.
The ramifications like so with the כהן kohen. *kohen* and the תרומה
trumah? *truma*, is there more application,
is it more כולל *kollel*? Right, it's also, yeah, so again, that's
specific technical issues that are used in terms of the question of
איסור חל על איסור *issur chal al issur*. But yes, that is
always a question, right? What's the scope of it? All right, let's
take a look. Now we're going to get exactly to this issue
about the כהן kohen *kohen*. תנו רבנן Tano Rabbanan, *Tanu rabbanan*. אני
כהן kohen וחברי כהן kohen *Ani kohen vechaveiri kohen*. Okay, I'm a
כהן kohen *kohen* and my friend is a כהן kohen *kohen*. So
now actually the original תוספתא *Tosefta* is clearer. The original תוספתא *Tosefta*
is: אני כהן Kohen וחברי כהן Kohen, *Ani kohen vechaveiri kohen*, and
the other person says: אני כהן Kohen? וחברי כהן Kohen. *Ani kohen
vechaveiri kohen*. Okay, so basically it becomes a case like our משנה
Mishna *mishna* where what you say about yourself we don't care, we
don't trust you, but each one is testifying about the other guy.
Okay, so it's basically the case of the משנה Mishna, *mishna*. All
right, let's see. This is now a restating of the case of
the משנה mishnah *mishna*. נאמן להאכילו בתרומה *Ne'eman le'achilo bitruma*, you can
feed the guy that he's testifying about תרומה trumah, *truma*, ואינו נאמן
להשיאו אשה Lehasi'o Isha, *ve'eino ne'eman lehasio isha*.
Okay, and here becomes the implication about why the consequences of a
כהן Kohen? *kohen*. You cannot marry him off a woman to him
until עד שיהיו ג' *ad sheyehiyu gimmel*, unless there are three people
there, not just two. שנים מעידים על זה ושנים מעידים על זה
shnayim me'idim al zeh ve-shnayim me'idim al zeh. *Shnayim me'idim al zeh
u'shnayim me'idim al zeh*. So sort of like when you would go
around and you do the התר נדרים *hetter nidarim*. Exactly. So first
you have two testify on one and then the other two testify
on the other. So anyway you need two witnesses to marry him
off a woman. Now what's the concern of marrying him off a
woman? Why as Dove pointed out, if he's a כהן Kohen, *kohen*,
that actually restricts the women that he can marry. So רש''י Rashi
*Rashi* says it just means because as we've seen before כהנים kohanim
*Kohanim* would be very careful to marry only women from a very
good ייחוס yuchus. *yichus*. So here's this woman from this very good
family from this really good ייחוס yuchus. *yichus*, she came over on
the Mayflower, and she came over with יהושע בן
נון *Yehoshua bin Nun*, and exactly with עזרא Ezra *Ezra*, and so
she's going to want a high degree of evidence. You know, those
families are going to want higher standard of proof that this guy's
a real כהן Kohen *kohen* before I let my daughter marry him.
So it's actually interesting because then it's not even so much halachically,
it's more like
socially, but we've seen that before that there's all this concern around
ייחוס yichus. *yichus* and so on. So okay, the practice that has
been adopted is that we're going to demand a higher level before
we do this even though there's very little halachic consequence involved. That's
one approach. The other approach is that we're concerned that maybe if
we don't know his status besides the question of whether he's a
כהן Kohen. *kohen* or not, forget about being a כהן Kohen *kohen*,
maybe he's a ממזר *mamzer*. So if we don't know what somebody's
background is, so that's what we believe him. We believe him not
just that he's a כהן Kohen, *kohen* but we believe him that
he's not a ממזר *mamzer* or anything like that. Of course, there's
a huge תוספות *Tosafot* here, the reason our דף *daf* is so
small is because there's a lot of discussion in תוספות *Tosafot*. So
there's a huge תוספות *Tosafot* that says we generally don't assume people
are ממזרים *mamzerim* even if we don't know their prior status. So
he doesn't buy that as the reason. Okay, so then תוספות *Tosafot*
finally says the real issue is about whether we would have to,
about what we believe that his kid will be. Like are we
going to להשיאו אשה *lehasio isha* really means because when you check
about who's the woman that you have marry a כהן Kohen, *kohen*,
it's not just good ייחוס *yichus*. You want to check that the
woman is not a חללה *chalala*. So saying that we're going to
check the woman to marry him, because then the חללה *chalala* the
kids
won't be considered כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim*. So what it means is if
we're saying we're checking to make sure the woman that he's going
to marry, it means we're going to be concerned about whether his
kids are חללים challalim *chalalim*. So it's really just a code word
for saying are we going to assume whether his kids are חללים
challalim *chalalim* or not? Now of course the funny thing is I
don't get it. If you're prepared to let him eat תרומה trumah
*truma* then why how is it different? Why would she be concerned
that his kids are חללים *chalalim*? I mean if he can eat
תרומה trumah *truma* his kids can eat תרומה truma, *truma*. So תוספות
*Tosafot*, okay, really it's not... תרומה. truma, Really what we're saying is
very convoluted because it's about the גמרא. Gemara Anyway he says really
it's about saying can we let him work in the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. So I don't know how he gets that from להשיאו
אשה, but again it's very funny because this is the question תוספות
asks. Who so he's a כהן, Kohen why is that... why does
that allow him to marry certain types of women? It should restrict
him from marrying certain types of women. So again the best two
answers are either what רש"י Rashi says, that it's a more societal
thing that מיוחס meyuchas families wouldn't want to marry their daughter off
to him unless they could prove with better proof that he's a
כהן. Kohen Or תוספות re-reads it to say it's really a question
of do we let him work in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
which is obviously a much more weighty issue than תרומה.
truma, Okay, as to the marrying thing, they were
more
מיקל meikel on תרומה?
truma. I guess it's תרומה דרבנן trumah de-rabbanan or something like that?
Well we'll see, but even if it's תרומה דאורייתא, trumah de-oraisa, still
working in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
you're מחלל mechallel the עבודה. avodah. No, that makes more sense, but
like okay, I'll let you eat תרומה, truma, oh no, I can't
let you marry my daughter.
Right, but that's a proof because it's not a halachic point, it's
a societal point. Families with good יחוס, yichus, I don't care what
you and your הלכה halacha says, you're not marrying my daughter unless
you can prove it. Okay, anyway, so alright, so anyway, okay, תנו
רבנן, rabbanan, so okay, that's so
anyway there's a difference between תרומה truma, and יוחסין yuchsin or you
know, marrying a woman, getting married. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda as we know in the משנה is
not prepared to believe the כהן Kohen on one another. אף אינו
נאמן לאכילה בתרומה. Af eino ne'eman le'achila be-trumah. No, even for תרומה
truma, you're not believed, עד שיהיו שלשה, ad she-yiheyu shlosha, שנים מעידים
על זה ושנים מעידים על זה. Okay, so fine,
so we basically in addition to introducing the idea that it doesn't
work for marriage, we basically just repeated the idea that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda does not believe the כהנים Kohanim to be made on
one another. Okay, so now the גמרא's Gemara going to ask a
question which is both on this ברייתא braita and on our משנה,
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is stricter than the חכמים chakhamim and
not prepared to believe. למימר דרבי יהודה חייש לגומלין? Lememar de-Rabbi Yehuda
chayeish le-gomlim?
It seems like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is concerned, minimally he's concerned
about issues of collusion and reciprocity, that maybe he doesn't believe in
עד אחד at all about a כהן Kohen. status, but minimally he
doesn't believe this case where there are two and they're testifying about
one another. רבנן לא חיישי לגומלין Rabbanan lo chayeshei le-gomlim and the
rabbis are not concerned about reciprocity. והאיפכא שמעינן להו, Ve-ha-ibcha sham'inan le-hu,
but we've heard the opposite that none. החמרים שנכנסו לעיר, Hachamarim she-nichnesu
le-ir,
so you have donkey drivers that entered into a city, ואמר אחד
מהם, ve-amar echad me-hem,
and basically they're not donkey drivers, they're also like, you know, it
means they're carrying their loads on their donkeys, they're merchants that go
from city to city, ואמר אחד מהם, ve-amar echad me-hem, and one
of them says, שלי חדש ושל חבירי ישן, sheli chadash ve-shel chaveiri
yashan,
my grain is חדש chadash grain, his is ישן yashan grain. שלי
אינו מתוקן, Sheli eino metukkan, my grain is not מתוקן metukkan for
תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u-ma'asros, meaning it's טבל, tevel, ושל חבירי מתוקן, ve-shel
chaveiri metukkan, and his has been taken תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u-ma'asros. So
he's basically saying his friend's grain is better than his. Okay, so
he's testifying about his friend. Now what is the idea of חדש
וישן? chadash ve-yashan? So the most obvious thing to say is that
similar to the תרומות ומעשרות trumos u-ma'asros issue, it means old grain
from before the עומר, omer, new grain after the עומר, omer, okay,
and that he's saying that actually my grain is אסור assur to
eat until פסח. Pesach. Okay, my friend's grain is old and it's
good. However, the problem is that the גמרא Gemara in a minute
is going to say that we're dealing with דרבנן de-rabbanan issues here,
not דאורייתא. de-oraisa. So that leads basically, so that's another big תוספות
figuring out what חדש וישן chadash ve-yashan is. Does it have to
do with שמיטה Shmita issues? At the end of the day, yeah,
anyway, at the end of the day תוספות and רש"י rashi both
say that the חדש וישן chadash ve-yashan is not about the כשרות
kashrus status of the grain. It's just in general saying bad stuff
about his. My friend has nice old dried grain which apparently is
better, like old wine is better, it's dried out. Mine is fresher
and it still hasn't been dried out, okay, which is worse. So
basically he's saying the מתוקן metukkan is clearly the halachic issue about
תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u-ma'asros. So basically he's saying all good stuff about
his friend. His grain is better, it's whatever, it's תרומות ומעשרות, trumos
u-ma'asros, mine is bad and so on. Okay, that's the story. So
can we believe them about... can we believe one guy about the
other? Of course the problem of collusion here is not like right
now they're testifying about one another, but in this city, right, you
say this and in the next city we switch and you say
the same thing about me.
Okay, and they both get to sell their grain.
Exactly.
So that's the question, do we believe them? It's a good deal,
right? Okay, so I have to tell this joke, which is, alright,
which is, so outside of Vatican City, you've heard this, there's two
guys, right? So one of them is like, you know, this Jew
with the scraggly beard and like in torn clothing and you know
looking miserable and with his like צדקה tzedaka box out. And then
there's another person, like priestly, you know, garments, the collar, big gold
cross, very refined, dignified. And everybody walks out of Vatican City, they
like spit at the Jew and they put like five dollars, ten
dollars, twenty dollars, you know, into the priest's, you know, carry box.
So finally somebody comes over to the Jew and he says, he
says, listen buddy, he says, you're not doing yourself any favors. You
know, listen, why don't you just leave here, go to the Jewish
quarter, go to your own people, and the people will take care
of you, they'll provide for you over there. So he looks up
to the priest and he says, חיים, Chaim, look who's telling us
how to do business.
Exactly, that is
the פשט
*pshat*, that is the joke for today's דף *daf*. Alright, exactly. Anyway,
so are we concerned about that? Okay, so
anyway,
alright
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
So okay, so אינו נאמן *eino ne'eman*,
he's not believed because we're afraid there's a whole collusion going on
here. רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda אומר נאמן *Rabbi Yehuda omer ne'eman*, he
is believed. Okay, so here רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is
prepared to believe one guy about the other and in our משנה
*Mishnah* not. So people, everybody's reversing their positions.
Isn't that what we're supposed to do, which means עדים *edim* with
them all the time like?
Yeah, I don't know. It's a good question. I don't know. I
don't know. How do we do it nowadays? I don't know. אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה אמר רב *Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava amar
Rav*, you develop a reputation. I don't know. מוחלפת השיטה *muchlefet hashita*.
Okay, you're right, it's reversed. The names got mixed up. Which is
a very reasonable position. So fine, so רבי יהודה rabbi yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* should be the one to say אינו נאמן *eino ne'eman* and
the חכמים chakhamim. *Chachamim* should be the ones to say נאמן *ne'eman*.
אביי אמר לעולם לא תהפוך *Abaye amar l'olam lo teihafuch*. No, let's
not reverse it. Let's try to understand how the cases might be
different. בדמאי הקלו *bidmai heikeilu*. Oh,
the case there, to say that the grain has had תרומות ומעשרות
*terumot u'ma'asrot* taken, even if we wouldn't say that, we wouldn't believe
them. What's the status of grain that you buy from an עם
הארץ *am ha'aretz*? It's דמאי demai *dmai*, because we anyway think that
most likely the עמי הארץ *amei ha'aretz* did take תרומות ומעשרות *terumot
u'ma'asrot*. It's just rabbinically we don't believe it. So since rabbinically we
don't believe it, it's sort of like שבויה *shvuyah*, right? רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* doesn't have a problem about believing the woman by the
case of שבויה *shvuyah*. שבויה הקלו *shvuyah heikeilu*. So דמאי הקלו *dmai
heikeilu*. Okay? So yeah, we're lenient in that case because the only
thing at stake there is the status of דמאי *dmai*, which is
only a rabbinic concern. Okay, so the גמרא gemara *Gemara*'s going to
ask that. So רבא אמר רוב עמי הארץ מעשרין הן *Rava amar
rov amei ha'aretz ma'asrin hen*. Most עמי הארץ *amei ha'aretz* take מעשר
*ma'aser*, so therefore it's only a rabbinic concern. So therefore רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda*'s willing to believe in that case. So the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* says אמר רבא דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה קשיא דרבנן d'rabbanan אדרבנן
לא קשיא *Amar Rava d'Rabbi Yehuda a'd'Rabbi Yehuda kashya d'rabbanan a'd'rabbanan lo
kashya*? Okay, what, you think only רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* is a
contradiction of his two positions and the rabbis are not a problem
about them contradicting what they said earlier? So רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
here is more, is more lenient and you've explained why he's more
lenient because it's דמאי *dmai*. But why are the rabbis more strict?
In our משנה *Mishnah* the rabbis are prepared to believe about a
כהן Kohen, *Kohen* and here they're not prepared to believe that the
grain is okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אלא דרבי יהודה
אדרבי יהודה לא קשיא כדשנינן *Ela d'Rabbi Yehuda a'd'Rabbi Yehuda lo kashya
kid'shaninan*. רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* isn't a problem like we said. He's
more lenient in this case about the דמאי *dmai* that's only rabbinic
and we're lenient. How about the rabbis? Why are they more strict
about the grain case? דרבנן d'rabbanan אדרבנן לא קשיא כדאמר רבי חמא
בר עוקבא בכלי אומנתו בידו *D'rabbanan a'd'rabbanan lo kashya k'de'amar Rabbi Chama
bar Ukva b'khlei uminuto b'yado*. Like what רבי חמא בר עוקבא *Rabbi
Chama bar Ukva* said,
when he has the instruments of his profession in his hand. הכא
נמי בכלי אומנתו בידו *Hacha nami b'khlei uminuto b'yado*. Here too he's
got the instruments of the profession in his hand. What does that
mean? So what רש"י rashi *Rashi* says it means is, is that
if the other guy who is testifying that my friend's grain is
the best, if basically he's got out all of his equipment, like
his scales and his, you know, cash register and the whole thing,
it's very clear that he's planning on selling his grain in the
next city. So therefore we're concerned about this whole reciprocity, whereas, you
know, if basically all of his stuff is packed up, and then
we won't assume that he's planning on selling his stuff in the
next city and therefore we'll be prepared to believe him about his
friend. Okay, which is a little bit funny because in the case
of a כהן Kohen, *Kohen*, they're both showing up and want תרומה
truma *terumah*. That should just like be כלי אומנתו בידו *khlei uminuto
b'yado*. It's clear that they both want to, that they both want
to, that they're both going to benefit from the testimony. It's not
exactly clear why that makes it any, why that makes it any
more of a basis of suspicion than the case of the כהן
Kohen *Kohen*. תוספות *Tosafot* says בכלי אומנתו בידו *b'khlei uminuto b'yado* is
in the opposite case. Why we do believe in the case of
the כהן Kohen. *Kohen*, because basically the כהן Kohen, *Kohen* has out
the type of vessels that are thing that would, you know, that
are particularly kept as טהור tahor. *tahor* vessels and other types of
things that sort of signify, like, and give us, you know, indications
that oh this person is probably a כהן Kohen. *Kohen*. Look, you
know, he's got all that כהונה kehunah. *kehunah* apparatus, you know, that
he's dealing with. So anyway, there's some type of special circumstances. It's
not clear in which case that that's being said about. Okay, so
now the גמרא *Gemara* says והיכא איתמר דרבי חמא בר עוקבא *V'heicha
itmar d'Rabbi Chama bar Ukva*? Where was this statement of רבי חמא
בר עוקבא *Rabbi Chama bar Ukva* originally said? אהא דתנן *Aha d't'nan*,
that which we taught, הקדר שהניח קדירותיו *Hakadar shehenniach kdeirotav*. So you
have the person who sells jugs, okay, and he basically leaves his,
you know, his jugs and his whatever, his pitchers, וירד לשתות *veyarad
lishtot*, and he went down to get a drink of water. Okay,
and the point is here is that the question is, did the
עם הארץ *am ha'aretz* right touch them and make them טמא tamai
*tamei*? Okay, and he left, he, you know, he abandoned them for
a few minutes to go get a drink of water. Okay. הפנימיות
טהורות tahoros? *Hapnimiyot tehorot*. The ones that are most, are innermost, which
are not sort of exposed to the street and where people are
passing by, are טהור tahor, *tahor*. You're not afraid that people touched
them. והחיצונות *V'hachitzonot*, the outermost ones, which are, you know, where people
could encounter them, טמאות tme'ot *tmeiot*, they're טמא *tamei* because maybe they
walked by and rubbed against them or touched them or whatever it
was. והתניא v'hatanya, *V'hatanya*, but didn't we teach in a ברייתא braita
*braita*, אלו ואלו טמאות *eilu v'eilu tmeiot*, that everything is טמא *tamei*,
even the innermost ones? So אמר רבי חמא בר עוקבא, amar rabbi
chama bar ukva, so בכשכלי אומנותו בידו, bich'sheklei umanuto b'yado, when his
instruments of his profession are in his hand. What does that mean?
It means that when the thing is set up and the jugs
are laid down and basically there's a cash register there and there's
a sign of for sale, you know, so then we're afraid that
people are going to be inspecting them and looking at them and
they're looking at even the ones that are in the back, you
know. Sometimes you go into the store and you can't find what
you're looking for and you keep on looking and maybe there's your
right size or whatever, you know, somewhere in the back. Okay, so
if it's clearly open for sale, open for business, then he has
to be concerned that they touched even the innermost ones. Otherwise, like
the guy hasn't opened his store yet, so you only have to
be concerned about the outermost ones. One minute, let's take a look.
Well, it's all yeah, it's tough. Gotta be concerned about דמאי and
about טומאה tumah and the whole thing. It was a very... a
very... an עירובין eiruvin can go in, it's sort of exactly. אמר
רבי חמא בר... amar rabbi chama bar... okay, where was it? Okay,
מפני שיד הכל ממשמש
בהן
mipnei she'yad hakol
memash'mesh
bahen because once the store is open
and like the, you know, instruments of the profession are out, then
everybody's going to look at them. והתניא, so but we have but
we have a third ברייתא brayta. that says the the other possibility.
אלו ואלו טהורות, eilu v'eilu tahoros, everything is טהור. אמר רבי חמא
בר עוקבא, בשאין כלי אומנותו בידו. b'she'ein klei umanuto b'yado. Okay, when
the store isn't open for business and his instruments aren't in his
hand. Okay, so but what's the middle case? והא דתנן הפנימיות טהורות
והחיצונות טמאות היכי משכחת לה? v'ha detnan hapnimiyot tahoros v'hachitzonot tme'ot heichi
mishkachat lah? So if the store's open everything is טמא and if
the store's closed everything is טהור, what's the case where the outer
ones are טמאות and the inner ones are טהורות? tahoros? I thought
this this stuff was like down by the river. It's not clear
where they are. But yeah, yes, a shop near the river. Okay,
you got your you know you laid out all your vessels. Or
a bus stop or whatever, he went to find the public restroom
or yeah, but doesn't mean it's at the shop.
It means, you know, you know those guys
who sell coffee on the street or whatever, you know those guys
who sell the books on the street, they have a table, they
have all their
books out, that's the guy. He laid out all his he laid
out
all of his his his his things
and then he went
for five minutes to go use a bathroom. Okay, so do you
start looking at the books or not? Is it clear that he's
already that he's set up for business? Maybe he opened his store
and you know and maybe he hasn't, like you know you know
they got that they know you know they got that plastic tarp,
right? So okay, let's say he hasn't removed the plastic tarp yet
or he's half removed it. You don't start looking until you know
the guy's open for business.
I would totally be looking at the books. Okay fine.
Anyway, alright. גמרא et cetera. Okay. So, okay. והא דתנן הפנימיות טהורות
והחיצונות טמאות היכי משכחת לה? v'ha detnan hapnimiyot tahoros v'hachitzonot tme'ot heichi
mishkachat lah? So what's the case at the outer ones we're afraid
of and the inner ones are still טהורות? דסמיכה לרשות הרבים. d'smicha
l'reshut harabbim. Okay, cause it's right at the edge of רשות הרבים,
reshut harabbim, so
even though it's
not yet open for business, it's right there, the outer ones are
right
there like aligned up against
רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, ומשום חיפופי רשות הרבים
u'mishum chifufei
reshut
harabbim and because of the rubbing of רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim, people
walk by it and even if they know the guy isn't open
for business yet and they're not going to consciously pick it up
and look at them, but they're going to touch them inadvertently and
therefore that's a problem. Okay, that was all a bit of a
digression. Okay. איבעית אימא, e'iba'it eima, back to the debate of רבי
יהודה and the רבנן, rabbanan which is why do their positions reverse
themselves between the כהן Kohen and the case about the grain. So,
ואיבעית אימא רבי יהודה ורבנן במעלין מתרומה ליוחסין קמיפלגי. v'iba'it eima rabbi
yehuda v'rabbanan b'ma'alin mi'truma l'yuchsin kamifligi. So this doesn't explain why the
רבנן rabbanan are going to be more strict by the grain case,
but it will explain why רבי יהודה is more lenient, is more...
I mean excuse me, why רבי... well, is more lenient by the
grain but let me say it the other way, why רבי יהודה
is more strict by the כהן. Kohen Why is it that we
find this strictness in our משנה regarding the כהן Kohen that we
don't find elsewhere? And even רבי יהודה is lenient in the case
of grain and he's strict in
this case. So the reason is because the כהן kohen presents special
special circumstances, special you know issues, concerns. The case of the כהן
is that if you let him eat תרומה, truma, which maybe we'd
be prepared to do, you're going to now assume that he's like
a מיוחס כהן. meyuchas kohen. Okay, and then again, so big deal,
assume he's מיוחס כהן. meyuchas kohen. So that might be the issue
we dealt with yesterday... on עמוד א. amud aleph. That families don't
want to marry off their daughters to him and whatever and we're
protecting families' ייחוס. Okay, not again, not such a halakhic issue, but
prefer... families' ייחוס. Or again, as תוספות says, once you're assuming יוחסין
yuchsin and he can marry the the חשובות chashuvot families, you're also
going to assume he's a כהן for all matters, even for working
in the בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. Okay, so it's the same issue
we dealt with before. So we saw that there was a higher
standard for יוחסין, yuchsin, whatever its implications are. So maybe if there's
a higher standard for יוחסין, yuchsin, that's exactly why we're not going
to believe him for תרומה, Terumah, because once you believe somebody about
תרומה, Terumah, it's going to be a slippery... then then people are
going to translate it into the other things as well. Okay. The
רבנן are more lenient. Okay, but this builds on, yes, so this
builds on what we introduced on עמוד א. amud aleph. On עמוד
א amud aleph we introduced that יוחסין yuchsin has a higher standard.
So now we understand why there might be an issue about תרומה.
Terumah If everybody agrees יוחסין yuchsin has a higher standard, I might
have to be forced to apply that to תרומה, Terumah, if once
I believe somebody about תרומה, Terumah people are going to translate it
for the other purposes as well. But you couldn't claim it had
a higher standard and still allowed him תרומה, Terumah you couldn't possibly
have that position right? Well you can, that's the חכמים. chakhamim The
חכמים say that יוחסין yuchsin has a higher standard, we allow him
to eat תרומה Terumah with an עד אחד and we're not afraid
that people will just say just cause he's eating תרומה, Terumah. it's
definite that he's a that he's a כהן even for יוחסין yuchsin
purposes. Well now, you understand, it's reasonable, the... issue about us translating
one to the next. So okay, so let's take a look. Okay,
so that's why the כהן is special. Okay, so now the גמרא
says like this. איבעיא להו, Iba'ilu, מהו להעלות משטרות ליוחסין. mahu le'haalos
mish'taros leyuchsin. So we've introduced that there's a debate of if somebody
eats תרומה, Terumah can we assume? Now by the way, I actually
misstated it a little bit. It's not just a question about are
we afraid that people are we afraid that people will translate one
to the other? You know, there's always a question about like which
comes first, the societal norms or the הלכה, Halacha, which sort of
shapes the other. But the phrase of מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין ma'alin mitrumah
leyuchsin means, right, are we halachically going to take the position that
if somebody eats תרומה, Terumah therefore he's good for יחוס Yichus purposes
as well? So if you say halachically we take that position, then
therefore we can't trust a guy for תרומה Terumah unless he satisfies
the status of יחוס, Yichus, because we have halachically adopted the position
that if he's eating תרומה, Terumah that's also good for יוחסין Yuchsin
purposes. So that's לא מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין. lo ma'alin mitrumah leyuchsin. The
other position that says מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין ma'alin mitrumah leyuchsin means we
are prepared that we are prepared to say if he's eating תרומה
Terumah halachically that means it's good for יחוס. Yichus. So because we're
going to halachically say to translate one to the other, therefore we
won't allow somebody to be believed for תרומה Terumah unless we are
prepared to believe for יחוס Yichus purposes. Where does הגמרא haGemara come
into this? We'll get to that. Okay. So again, מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין
ma'alin mitrumah leyuchsin means
halachically we will translate one to the
other and therefore we have to apply the same standard for both.
אין מעלין Ein ma'alin means halachically we will not translate one to
the other and therefore we're allowed to apply different standards for the
two of them. Okay. So now the גמרא says like this. איבעיא
להו, Iba'ilu, they raised a question. מהו להעלות משטרות ליוחסין. mahu le'haalos
mish'taros leyuchsin. If you have a שטר that has somebody's name in
it and identifies him as a כהן, okay, can you treat that
as strong enough evidence to allow the guy for יוחסין Yuchsin purposes
which we've established, again, that יוחסין Yuchsin
is the highest standard. So היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case?
אילימא דכתיב ביה, Ilima d'chsiv bei, אני פלוני כהן חתמתי עד. Ani
ploni Kohen chasamti eid.
If he's the guy that's one of the עדים and says, you
know, ראובן בן אהרן הכהן, Reuven ben Aharon HaKohen, right, עד. So
then the גמרא says
why would that be good testimony for, you know, he's just testifying
about himself? So מאן קמססהיד ליה? Man kamsahid lei?
Who's testifying about him? He's just testifying about himself. How could that
serve as evidence that he's a real כהן? So גמרא says לא
צריכא דכתיב ביה, lo tzericha d'chsiv bei, אני פלוני כהן לויתי מנה
מפלוני. Ani ploni Kohen livisi maneh miploni. I, ראובן הכהן, Reuven HaKohen,
borrowed money from שמעון, Shimon, וחתימו סהדי, v'chasimu sahadei, and the and
there are witnesses signed on the bottom.
So the witnesses are signing on the bottom of a document in
which somebody's identified as a כהן. Does that mean that the witnesses
are also testifying to the fact that he is a כהן? Probably
not. They're just signing to the loan. So מאי? Mai? אמנה
שבשטר קמססהדי. a'maneh shebash'tar kamsahadei. Bottom line, the witnesses are, you know,
are not paying attention to making sure all the names are right.
They're basically testifying to the fact that the loan took place and
they should not be interpreted to understand to testify to other things
that are not, you know, central to the actual case at hand.
או דילמא אכולה מילתא קמססהדי? O dilma achula milsa kamsahadei? Or maybe
that once their witnesses their signatures are on the bottom, they're testifying
to all aspects of the document? It's a good question. So רב
הונא ורב חסדא. Rav Huna v'Rav Chisda. חד אמר מעלין, Chad amar
ma'alin, one says if you have a document and somebody's identified in
it as an עד and it's signed at the bottom as a
כהן, you can assume that the guy's a כהן even for the
higher standard of יוחסין. Yuchsin. וחד אמר אין מעלין, V'chad amar ein
ma'alin, and the other says you cannot. Okay. איבעיא להו. Iba'ilu. So
that was one question, going from document. By the way, since we're
learning כתובות, Kesubos, it's very relevant because a whole issue like, you
know, of the כתובה, Kesubah, there's a lot of הקפדה hakpadah in
the כתובה, Kesubah, because bottom line is, you know, how many people
are using the כתובה Kesubah for real דיני ממונות dinei mamonus type
of purposes as was intended, but there's an issue about if a
woman is a גרושה gerusha or a גיורת giyores to be careful
to either say it explicitly or indicate that, you know, not just
because then it's a difference of a hundred or two hundred, but
because then you have a document that has stating her personal status
and that would be personal status that would be relevant for other
הלכות halachos like marrying a כהן. What are the names? So a
lot of people just do מטרחתא, matrachta, which means
גיורת, giyores, as opposed
to בתולתא, besulta, or they say גיורתא. giyorta. So what if there's
other ways to subtly indicate it if there's sensitivity around that?
Divorce is מטרחתא matrachta and a גיורת giyores is גיורתא.
giyorta. So you don't read it out loud. Well, you don't read
it out loud. Like the, yeah, often the groom is the groom
is identified as
a כהן if he is
a כהן, but we
don't have to
but anyway, but this is anyway, that issue about what you assume
based on written documents is an important question. So that's one issue
about assuming יוחסין, Yuchsin, which we know is the highest standard, based
on written documents. Now we have another question. איבעיא להו, Iba'ilu, they
raise a question. מהו להעלות מנשיאת כפים ליוחסין? Mahu le'haalos menesi'as kapayim
leyuchsin? If somebody is duchening, can we then is that a good
enough to base it on as evidence for the higher standard of
the marriage issue? Okay. So the גמרא says תיבעי למאן דאמר מעלין
מתרומה ליוחסין ותיבעי למאן דאמר אין מעלין. tiba'i leman d'amar ma'alin mitrumah
leyuchsin v'tiba'i leman d'amar ein ma'alin. And this we could ask this
question whatever your position is about whether we translate eating תרומה Terumah.
regard to יוחסין, Yuchsin, the duchening could be different than eating תרומה.
Terumah Why is that? There's no money, right? Well, right. But okay,
let's take a look. Yeah, but that's true. So תיבעי למאן דאמר
מעלין. tiba'i leman d'amar ma'alin. Even according to the one that says
that if he's eating תרומה Terumah we can assume he's... Maybe נשיאת
כפים nesiat kapayim is different. Why? איבעיא למאן דאמר מעלין, tiba'i leman
de'amar ma'alin, הני מילי hani mili תרומה Terumah, דעוון מיתה היא de'avon
mita hi because תרומה Terumah, is a very weighty thing. If he's
not a כהן, he's חייב מיתה chayav mita if it's תרומה דאורייתא.
Terumah de'Oraisa.
But נשיאת כפים, nesiat kapayim,
if a non-כהן does דוכנין, duchanin, so the איסור עשה, issur asei,
that's only a מצוות עשה, mitzvas asei, כה תברכו את בני ישראל,
Koh sevarchu es bnei Yisrael, only כהנים, Kohanim, you bless ישראל, Yisrael,
not others. So just because he's doing דוכנין, duchanin, he might be
willing to be a non-כהן or a questionable כהן and big deal,
I'll דוכנין. duchanin. Okay, so therefore we can't assume that somebody who
is דוכנין duchanin is necessarily proven to our satisfaction that he's a
כהן. לא. So therefore we cannot translate that into יוחסין. yuchsin. או
דילמא, od dilma, or do we say לא שנא? lo shna? No,
even something like נשיאת כפים, nesiat kapayim, he wouldn't do it if
he weren't a כהן, and therefore, or the community wouldn't let him
do it if he weren't a כהן, and therefore if he's doing
it, it must be that that's a high enough degree of proof
for us. Can we just allow him to do it? איבעיא, tiba'i,
that's always the question: how did he start doing it? Like, but
now he's been doing it and that's the practice. So it's a
combination of the fact that he's doing it and that the society
is allowing it that serves as the evidence in which we're trying
to figure out a status. Doesn't mean the same thing as an
עליה? aliyah? That's the same idea? Maybe. Not really because at least
here you have an איסור עשה issur asei issue, so it has
some weight to it. איבעיא למאן דאמר אין מעלין, tiba'i leman de'amar
ein ma'alin, and you could ask the question the opposite way: even
if you're not prepared to translate תרומה trumah. to יוחסין, yuchsin, you
might be prepared to translate this. Why? הני מילי hani mili תרומה
trumah, דמיתאכלה בצינעה demisachla betzina because that gets my point here back
to who's doing it and who's allowing it. תרומה trumah is eaten
in private, so therefore, the community, it's not like the community has
recognized him as a כהן and let him eat תרומה. trumah. He
goes to two or three farmers who have a little compassion on
him and they give him תרומה trumah, even though they
don't necessarily 100 percent believe.
So the fact that he's eating תרומה trumah for his own עבירות
aveiros is a big deal, but it doesn't prove a sense of
communal recognition that he's a כהן. Okay, אבל נשיאת כפים דבפרהסיא, aval
nesiat kapayim defarhesya, but דוכנין duchanin that happens in public, אי לאו
כהן הוא, ilav Kohen hu, if he were not a כהן, כולי
האי לא מחציף איניש לנפשיה. kulei hai lo machtzif inish lanafshai. So
I've been trying to say the community wouldn't allow it; it's saying
that a person wouldn't have the חוצפה chutzpah to get up there
in front of the whole community if it weren't actually true. Okay,
so there's different factors we could look at to determine how good
is the evidence that the person really is a כהן. And again,
recognizing that the highest standard is יוחסין, yuchsin, and therefore how much
if he does other things that normally only a כהן does, can
that satisfy our high standards for the יוחסין yuchsin purposes.
The community, whatever you want to call it, display may be more
weighty than a private דאורייתא. de'Oraisa. Exactly. Yeah, okay. או דילמא לא
שנא, od dilma lo shna, I'm sorry, okay,
just had to read those words, but maybe it doesn't matter. Yeah.
Do you have anything to say about the fact that eating תרומה,
trumah, a non-כהן תרומה, trumah, is a capital offense?
It's מיתה בידי שמים, mita bidei shamayim, not at least in the
court. Okay, I don't know, I don't have anything to say about
that.
Okay, fine. Now, רב חסדא ורב אבינא, Rav Chisda ve-Rav Avina, so
that's the question. רב חסדא ורב אבינא, Rav Chisda ve-Rav Avina, חד
אמר מעלין, chad amar ma'alin, you can translate from נשיאת כפים nesiat
kapayim to יוחסין, yuchsin, וחד אמר אין מעלין, ve-chad amar ein ma'alin,
no, הלכה-ly halachic we cannot assume just because he's דוכנין duchanin that
he's a proven enough כהן for יוחסין yuchsin purposes. אמר ליה רב
נחמן בר יצחק לרבא: amar lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak le-Rava: מהו
להעלות מנשיאת כפים? mahu le-ha'alos mi-nesiat kapayim? Did I just read that?
Oh no, okay, but it's the same question; it's just now he's
asking as opposed to a general איבעיא להו, iba'i lehu, now we
have actually asked, have one אמורא amora asking the other. So, אמר
ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק לרבא: amar lei Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
le-Rava: מהו להעלות מנשיאת כפים ליוחסין? mahu le-ha'alos mi-nesiat kapayim le-yuchsin? So
what's the story, can we or not? אמר ליה: amar lei: פלוגתא
דרב חסדא ורב אבינא.
pelugta de-Rav
Chisda ve-Rav Avina.
It's a debate of רב חסדא Rav Chisda and רב אבינא. Rav
Avina. So he says, fine, הלכתא מאי? hilchesa mai? That wasn't what
I was asking; what's the הלכה? halacha? אמר ליה: amar lei: אנא
מתניתא ידענא. ana masnisa yadena. He says, look, what I know is
a ברייתא. brayta? Okay, what's the ברייתא? brayta, דתניא, detanya, we learn
in a ברייתא, braisa רבי יוסי אומר: Rabbi Yosei omer: גדולה חזקה,
gedola chazaka, חזקה chazaka is very weighty, שנאמר, shene'emar, because it says
the following, and here's a statement in עזרא relating to the כהנים
Kohanim that returned from the גולה, gola, and a lot of them
were intermarried. Right, so the whole problem therefore about certain כהנים, Kohanim,
they might be חללים because their parent, father might have been intermarried.
Meaning they might be. Well, if their father, they might be חללים
if their father did intermarry. ומבני הכהנים בני חביה בן הקוץ בני
ברזילי אשר לקח מבנות ברזילי הגלעדי אשה ויקרא על שמם אלה בקשו
כתבם המתיחשים.
umibnei hakohanim bnei Chavaya ben Hakotz bnei Barzillai asher lakach mibnos Barzillai
ha-Giladi isha vayikarei
al shemam eileh bikshu kesavam hamityachasim. So these כהנים kohanim, from this
family looked for their document of יחוס, yichus, right? Their document of
genealogy. So by the way, the whole idea of יוחסין yuchsin and
all of this, and we'll get even more of this concerning
קידושין, Kiddushin, thank you, on
and on, and in קידושין, Kiddushin, a whole פרק that deals with
this stuff, is these are concerns that go way back, right, again,
and they're deep, deep societal concerns.
So again, as we've been pointing out,
it's not clear what the הלכה halachic weight about some of this
stuff is, but obviously families of יחוס yichus always want to, it's
like a America's a classless society, so we don't appreciate this as
much, but I guess for people that watch, what's the name of
that show, Downton Abbey or whatever, you understand that class makes a
huge difference, and you only marry within your class and so on.
Anyway, but for כהנים, kohanim, it could be Be an issue of
of חלל, chalal, of being a חלל chalal as well, or you
know, or as we've been discussing. So let's take a look. Okay,
so חלל chalal or even a non, you know, non-Jew if the
mother wasn't Jewish, but anyway. Okay, so these כהנים, kohanim. this is
a פסוק. pasuk. We're looking for their, for their documentation of their
genealogy, of their ייחוס. ולא נמצאו v'lo nimtzu and they could not
produce it. ויגעלו מן הכהונה, vayigalu min hakehunah, ויגואלו מן הכהונה, vayigo-alu
min hakehunah, רש"י rashi says, and they were despised, they were rejected
from the כהונה. kehunah ויאמר התרשתא, vayomer hatirshatha, התרשתא hatirshatha says, התרשתא
hatirshatha is נחמיה, nechemia, להם, lahem, אשר לא יאכלו מקדש הקדשים, asher
lo yochlu mikodesh hakodashim, they cannot eat from the קרבנות, korbanot, from
the holy of holies, understood to be the קרבנות, korbanot, עד עמוד
כהן לאורים ותומים ad amod kohen l'urim v'tumim until משיח mashiach comes,
which is basically, okay guys, until משיח mashiach comes and proves otherwise,
you can't eat from the because there was no אורים ותומים urim
v'tumim in the second בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. Yeah, but they don't
know who's their mother, we don't know, there's all these questions about
what happens in the גלות. golus. Okay, so that's the פסוק. pasuk.
So now we're going to interpret, we're going to focus on the
word קדש הקדשים. kodesh hakodashim. אמר להם, amar lahem, so נחמיה nechemia
said to them, הרי אתם בחזקתכם, harei atem b'chezkatchtem, so you retained
the status you had in exile. במה הייתם אוכלים בגולה, b'meh hayitem
ochlim bagolah, what were you eating in exile? בקדשי גבול, b'kodshei gvul,
in the קדשים kodshim that were eaten outside of the בית המקדש,
beit hamikdash, meaning תרומה. trumah אף כאן בקדשי גבול, af kan b'kodshei
gvul, fine, you can continue eating תרומה, trumah, but not קדש הקדשים.
kodesh hakodashim. It's focusing on the word קדש הקדשים, kodesh hakodashim, not
קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so ואי סלקא דעתך, v'isalkadaysach, okay, that's all very
nice. What does that? So that's גדולה חזקה, gdola chazakah, that the
fact that you had been eating by תרומה trumah even though now
we see that you can't produce any documentation, we're going to let
you continue eating תרומה. trumah? That's the point of that ברייתא of
גדולה חזקה. gdola chazakah. Now why is this relevant for us? So
let's take a look. ואי סלקא דעתך מעלין מנשיאות כפים ליוחסין, v'isalkadaysach
maalin min nesiat kapayim l'yuchsin, if you say that in general you
can go from דוכנין duchaning to יוחסין, yuchsin, הני כיון דפרסי ידייהו,
hani keivan d'parsi yadaihu, these כהנים, kohanim right, if they continue to
do what they were doing in the exile, when in the exile
they weren't just eating תרומה, trumah they were often actually also doing
דוכנין. duchaning. So if they're, so presumably if we're saying גדולה חזקה,
gdola chazakah, they're going to continue to דוכן duchan now that they're
back in ארץ ישראל. eretz yisrael. Okay, but if the, and if
we would say that from דוכנין duchaning you can get to יוחסין,
yuchsin, but the whole problem here is, is that we're not going
to fully prepare to embrace you as כהנים. And יוחסין yuchsin is
saying we're embracing you, and נחמיה nechemia here is telling them, you're
not going to be embraced, you're not going to work in the
בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. So ואי סלקא דעתך מעלין מנשיאות כפים ליוחסין
הני כיון דפרסי ידייהו, v'isalkadaysach maalin min nesiat kapayim l'yuchsin hani keivan
d'parsi yadaihu, if they're going to do, if they're going to דוכן,
duchan, אתי לאסוקינהו, ati l'asukinu, they're going to raise them up to
a full status of כהונה and they'll let them work in the
בית המקדש beit hamikdash and that was exactly the point that we
were trying to avoid. So clearly if he's letting them do what
they used to do, right, then it must be that the דוכנין
duchaning will not translate into יוחסין. yuchsin. So the גמרא says, no.
שאני הכא דריע חזקייהו. shani hacha d'raiah chezkaihu. No, no, no, here
it's different. Here everybody knows that their status has been put into
question. Okay, you know, the פסוק pasuk says they were from this
family, actually בני ברזילי bnei barzillai is a non-כהן family. Anyway, רש"י
says everybody knows their status in question because everybody knows they're not
working in the בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. So this was special circumstances
that there had been a stigma on the family. Okay, so there
we're going to not be concerned, but in other cases we will
say that you can translate from one to the other. Okay, the
גמרא says ואי לא תימא הכי, v'ilu teima hachi, if you don't
say this was a special case, so למאן דאמר מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין,
l'man d'amar maalin mitrumah l'yuchsin, you have the same question you just
asked me if you translate from תרומה trumah. to יוחסין, yuchsin, because
it's clear that they continue to eat תרומה, trumah. right? So if
they continue to eat תרומה, trumah then, then we would say, oh,
they're totally מיוחס meyuchas כהנים and they can work in the בית
המקדש, beit hamikdash, but that's what we were trying to avoid. So
כיון דאכלי בתרומה אתי לאסוקינהו, keivan d'achli bitrumah ati l'asukinu, you're going
to raise them up to the full status. Okay, the word אסוקינהו
asukinu is the parallel the Hebrew מעלין. maalin. אלא לאו משום דריע
חזקייהו, ella lav mishum d'raiah chezkaihu, it must be because their status
has been stigmatized and thrown into question, so in this case nobody's
going to translate from one to the other. Let's read a few
more lines. דף כה עמוד א. daf chaf hey amud aleph. ואלא
מאי גדולה חזקה, v'ella mai gdola chazakah, what's so great about the
חזקה? chazakah? Okay, you know, if they were eating תרומה trumah they
continue to eat תרומה, trumah. what's the big חידוש? chiddush. Okay, it's
not that we can and we're not going to translate the eating
תרומה trumah into anything else. So what's the חידוש chiddush? of eating
תרומה? trumah So מעיקרא אכל בתרומה דרבנן והשתא אכל בתרומה דאורייתא. meikara
achol bitrumah d'rabbanan v'hasha achol bitrumah d'oraita. Ah, in חוץ לארץ chutz
laaretz the תרומה Terumah, was only דרבנן d'rabbanan תרומה. Terumah. So the
big חידוש is not that it is that we're now going to
let you continue doing it even though you're in ארץ ישראל eretz
yisrael and you're going to come to eat תרומה דאורייתא, trumah d'oraita,
that is a big חידוש. Okay, even though we have a whole
question of your status. ואיבעית אימא, v'ibaitaima, if you want I could
tell you, הכא נמי בתרומה דרבנן אכל, hacha nami bitrumah d'rabbanan achol,
even in ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael they only eat דרבנן d'rabbanan. תרומה.
Terumah, What's the דרבנן d'rabbanan תרומה Terumah. in ארץ ישראל? eretz yisrael?
So רש"י says it's something that is not of the like grain
and oil and wine, like תרומה Terumah of פירות peirot is דרבנן.
d'rabbanan. So we would only let them continue to eat דרבנן Derabbanan,
תרומה. Terumah בתרומה דאורייתא לא אכל, bitrumah d'oraita lo achol, not biblical
תרומה Terumah, because actually we shouldn't allow them if we have this
big question. So וכי מסקינן מתרומה ליוחסין, v'chi maskinu mitrumah l'yuchsin, and
this by the way answers our other question about how we won't
translate from one to the other. When do we translate from eating
תרומה to יוחסין? yuchsin? בתרומה דאורייתא, bitrumah d'oraita, but בתרומה דרבנן לא
מסקינן, bitrumah d'rabbanan lo maskinan, not by דרבנן. But בתרומה דרבנן beTerumah
Derabbanan לא עסקינן, lo askinan, not by rabbinic תרומה, we only would
do it by biblical. And therefore we were not concerned that they
would come to give them full status, because we're only continuing to
let them eat rabbinic תרומה. דאמר מה גדולה חזקה, de'amar mah gedolah
chazakah, but if that's true, then we get back to our other
question. So what's the חידוש? They were eating rabbinic תרומה, they continue
to eat rabbinic תרומה. Okay, so and we're not afraid that therefore
it's going to translate. But okay, but then now what's, oh, look
how powerful חזקה chazakah is. What's the big deal? You know? So
the גמרא says, ah, the big deal is the following, דאף על
גב דאיכא למיגזר משום תרומה דאורייתא לא גזרינן. de'af al gav d'ika
lemigzar mishum Terumah Deorayta lo gazrinan. Eating rabbinic תרומה in חוץ לארץ
Chutz La'aretz is not a big deal. It's all it's a דרבנן,
but it won't lead to anything bad. But eating rabbinic תרומה in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you could say, you know, hey, if I'm
eating rabbinic תרומה, I'll start eat תרומה דאורייתא. Terumah Deorayta. And nevertheless,
we don't make, we're not going to make that גזירה. gezeirah. Okay,
so more on this tomorrow. Look at that, we got ahead and
we ended early. So practically...